<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of allegiance in our present circumstances consider'd in a letter from a minister in the city to a minister in the country.</title>
            <author>Masters, Samuel, 1645 or 6-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1067</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7622</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12990357</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12990357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50102)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96317)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 390:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of allegiance in our present circumstances consider'd in a letter from a minister in the city to a minister in the country.</title>
                  <author>Masters, Samuel, 1645 or 6-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Samuel Masters. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>In this ed. the last line of the text reads: committed and to accept the services of.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Allegiance --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:96317:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96317:1"/>
            <p>THE CASE of ALLEGIANCE CONSIDER'D</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:96317:2"/>
            <p>Let this be Printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Fraſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> 21. 8 8/9.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96317:2"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF ALLEGIANCE IN OUR Preſent Circumſtances CONSIDER'D. In a LETTER from a Miniſter in the City, to a Miniſter in the Country.</p>
            <q>Rom. 4.22. <hi>Happy is he that condemneth not himſelf in that thing which he alloweth.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96317:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96317:3"/>
            <head>THE CASE OF ALLEGIANCE CONSIDER'D.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU having thought fit to conſult my Judgment about the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>transferring</hi> our <hi>Allegiance</hi> from the <hi>late</hi> to the <hi>preſent KING;</hi> I ſhall not miſpend time in bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ill choice of ſo incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent a <hi>Caſuiſt.</hi> for ſo important a <hi>Caſe;</hi> but according to the Laws of that <hi>Friendſhip</hi> which have been for ſome time obſerv'd between us, I ſhall endeavour to approve my <hi>readineſs,</hi> if not my <hi>ability</hi> in ſerving you:</p>
            <p>I muſt not diſſent from you, in profeſſing a very tender and awful regard of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> whoſe Authority I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg to be ſacred and inviolable, and in the neglect of which I expect no peace in my own mind, nor any confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence toward God: and I think it neceſſary to add, That we ought to take as much care to <hi>inform</hi> our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> as to <hi>follow</hi> them; that we provide them all poſſible helps
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96317:4"/>and advantages; that we place Truths in the faireſt light, and view them with a ſteddy unprejudic'd Eye: And we who are <hi>Miniſters</hi> are more eſpecially concern'd to do ſo, who being appointed Guides, not only to our ſelves, but alſo to others, muſt beware of the double guilt of <hi>miſleading</hi> our Flock, by going our ſelves <hi>aſtray</hi> before them.</p>
            <p>You may believe me, Sir, as far as I can know my ſelf, that I have no <hi>Antimonarchical</hi> Principles, or ſecret diſguſt to the Perſon of the late King, to alienate my mind from him: Neither am I conſcious of any angry reſentments of <hi>former</hi> Sufferings, or of any diſcontent with my <hi>preſent</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or of any ambitious deſign, or hope of a <hi>future</hi> advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to bend my Inclinations to a concurrence with the preſent <hi>Revolution;</hi> for I ſolemnly proteſt, That if the late <hi>KING</hi> would have thought fit to continue his Government over us, though with many <hi>tolerable</hi> Inconveniences to the <hi>Publick,</hi> and though with any <hi>intolerable</hi> Prejudices to my <hi>private</hi> Intereſt, I would never have retracted my <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to his <hi>Authority,</hi> nor have deſiſted to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede with Heaven for bleſſings on his <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Whatever <hi>change</hi> therefore it made on my mind, it did not, I aſſure you, proceed from any <hi>deſign</hi> or <hi>choice</hi> of my own, but was neceſſarily induc'd from a <hi>change</hi> without, and from thoſe new Circumſtances into which the late <hi>King</hi> unexpectedly caſt us.</p>
            <p>It is indeed very <hi>difficult,</hi> as you complain, to determine the preſent Caſe with a ſatisfactory <hi>clearneſs</hi> and <hi>certitude,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is <hi>complicated</hi> of a great <hi>variety</hi> of things, ſome of which are <hi>foreign</hi> to our <hi>faculty,</hi> and which for the moſt part require a great niceneſs of thought to apprehend and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them; becauſe alſo we are yet ſcarce got out of the <hi>amazement</hi> into which ſo great a <hi>Revolution</hi> hath ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd us, and muſt have time to <hi>recollect</hi> and <hi>compoſe</hi> our thoughts, ere we can conſider ſo <hi>exactly,</hi> or deliberate ſo <hi>ſteddily</hi> as ſuch an Affair deſerves; but chiefly becauſe we have of late years imbib'd ſome falſe <hi>Maxims</hi> and Notions, which unhappily <hi>intangle</hi> our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>prejudice</hi> our minds againſt that <hi>truth,</hi> which it is now become our intereſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96317:4"/>to diſcover and acknowledg; and have had thoſe <hi>Notions</hi> inculcated upon us with ſo much <hi>force</hi> and <hi>importunity,</hi> that through a <hi>ſlaviſh fear</hi> of thoſe who have been a long time <hi>practiſing</hi> upon us, we have almoſt loſt our liberty of <hi>thinking freely,</hi> and <hi>judging impartially</hi> of theſe matters. Yet theſe <hi>difficulties</hi> are not <hi>inſuperable</hi> to an <hi>honeſt inquiſitive</hi> mind; they may indeed prompt us to excuſe candidly the <hi>Errors</hi> of others, and to ſeek more earneſtly for <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> to him that hath promis'd to <hi>give</hi> it to thoſe that <hi>lack,</hi> without <hi>upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> but ſhould rather <hi>animate</hi> than <hi>diſcourage</hi> our induſtry in the reſearches of a Truth wherein our <hi>Conſciences</hi> are ſo much concern'd.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being premis'd, I will now ſet cloſe to my Work; and upon a general view of the Deſign before me, I find it neceſſary for me to do theſe three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To diſcover and remove ſome <hi>falſe Principles</hi> about Government and Obedience, whence the <hi>obſcurities</hi> and <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties</hi> in the preſent Caſe do chiefly ariſe.</item>
               <item>2. To reſolve the chief <hi>difficulties</hi> in the Caſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</item>
               <item>3. To prove that <hi>Reſolution</hi> to be conſiſtent with all the Obligations that can affect a good <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It will be neceſſary in the firſt place to detect and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card thoſe falſe principles of Government and Obedience which have been in this laſt Age too earneſtly obtruded, and too eaſily entertain'd among us; and which are as a falſe biaſs on our minds to miſlead their Conſiderations, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray them into Error.</p>
            <p>And if we find ſuch Principles do rather <hi>inſlave</hi> than <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige</hi> our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and are as inconſiſtent with <hi>Truth,</hi> as they are with the preſent <hi>Revolution,</hi> we muſt take the honeſt courage, to break off thoſe bands, and aſſert our Liberty. Of this kind are chiefly theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a <hi>Monarchical</hi> form of Government, and the appropriation of it to a particular Perſon or Family, is <hi>jure
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96317:5"/>Divino,</hi> or by a <hi>Divine Right.</hi> How boldly this Principle hath been aſſerted by ſome men, you and I cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant; upon which ſo great a ſtreſs hath been laid, that to alter the <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> hath been thought as lewd an impiety as to alter either of the <hi>Holy Sacraments</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> to <hi>divert</hi> the Succeſſion, as unlawful as to <hi>pervert</hi> the very Courſe of Nature; and to oppoſe a King, tho is the moſt illegal extravagancies, or barbarous outrages, to be no leſs than fighting againſt God. If indeed ſuch a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right</hi> did appear, it muſt be acknowledged in diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inviolable, whatever ſad conſequences attend it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but upon examination we ſhall find that God hath no where inſtituted ſuch a <hi>Right,</hi> but ſome men have with too bold a fraud, made uſe of his Name to advance and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their unreaſonable pretenſions. If by ſuch a <hi>Divine Right,</hi> no more were intended than God's <hi>permiſſion</hi> and <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance,</hi> it would have no Opponents; for we know of no <hi>Law</hi> that doth forbid a <hi>Monarchical</hi> form of Government, or exclude <hi>any</hi> particular <hi>perſon</hi> or <hi>family</hi> from the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it: But then the pretence ſo interpreted, will not be ſufficient to render an <hi>alteration</hi> in the <hi>Government</hi> or <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> a ſin againſt God, as the aſſertors of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have ſometimes pretended. They therefore who plead this Argument, muſt be thought to aſſert, That God hath by ſome Law or Conſtitution appointed <hi>Monarchy</hi> to be the <hi>ſpecific</hi> form of Civil Government; and that the Crown ſhould be entail'd on ſuch particular perſons ſucceeding in the ſame Family, whereby the one cannot be chang'd, or the other debar'd without tranſgreſſing a Divine Inſtitution. This being a matter of great importance, and of common continual concernment to mankind, we may reaſonably expect, that if God hath made any ſuch <hi>Law,</hi> it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <hi>promulg'd</hi> to the World with <hi>ſufficient</hi> evidence and certainty; but tho many have been for ſome years moſt ſollicitouſly ſeeking after it, yet they are not agreed among themſelves in the <hi>diſcovery,</hi> nor can direct us where we may certainly meet with it. I know but of two ſort of <hi>Laws</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96317:5"/>which God hath given to mankind, Either <hi>Moral,</hi> impreſs'd on the human Nature; or <hi>Poſitive,</hi> reveal'd in the Holy <hi>Scriptures;</hi> but the <hi>jus divinum</hi> in diſpute is a ſtranger to <hi>both.</hi> God hath indeed by <hi>both,</hi> inſtituted <hi>Government,</hi> or <hi>Civil Authority</hi> for the welfare and ſecurity of men in their Civil Societies; He hath alſo commanded, that <hi>Superiors</hi> govern <hi>juſtly</hi> and <hi>mercifully,</hi> and that <hi>Inferiors</hi> honour them with <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſion:</hi> But I no where find that God hath commanded all Nations, or ours in particular, to be under that form of <hi>Government,</hi> which in contradiſtinction to other forms is called <hi>Monarchy;</hi> or under ſome particular Perſon or Family in contradiſtinction to all others. The <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> doth indeed erect a <hi>Monarchy</hi> in <hi>Families,</hi> over thoſe who are naturally deſcended from him that is to Govern; but there being not the ſame <hi>natural reaſon</hi> in our <hi>Civil Societies,</hi> there is not the ſame <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the ſame <hi>Government:</hi> And if ſome plead a <hi>likeneſs,</hi> or <hi>analogie</hi> between them, That can ſerve only for a <hi>rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal illuſtration,</hi> but not for any <hi>Logical proof,</hi> ſuch as the preſent caſe requires. From the Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> we learn that God did once inſtitute a <hi>Monarchy</hi> for the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and appointed particularly that <hi>David</hi> ſhould be their <hi>King,</hi> and alſo <hi>intail'd</hi> the Crown upon his Poſterity; but as God had particular Reaſons for that inſtitution, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> ſo we have no Reaſon to think that God intended by that inſtitution, to oblige any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but the <hi>Jews</hi> only. In the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> we find <hi>Civil</hi> Government ſuppos'd, and the <hi>moral</hi> Duties to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd both by ſuperiors and inferiors, deſcrib'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd, beyond what they are in any other inſtitutions; but we no where find <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> preſcribing the particular form of <hi>Civil Government,</hi> or preferring <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> or condemning an <hi>Ariſtocratic</hi> or <hi>Democratic</hi> ſtate; and much leſs determining the particular perſons or families on whom the <hi>Regal Dignity</hi> ſhall deſcend. Some indeed have inferr'd from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s aſſertions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular forms of Government, and the particular perſons which adminiſter it, are by a <hi>Divine Inſtitution;</hi> but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they countenance this miſtake from our <hi>Engliſh</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96317:6"/>which ſays, <hi>There is no power but of God, the powers that are, are ordained of God;</hi> yet the Text is incapable of ſuch a ſenſe, if we read and render it exactly according to the Original.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in an exact Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would run thus; <hi>There is no Authority, if not of God; and the Authorities which are</hi> (of God's Inſtitution) <hi>are ordered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God.</hi> The plain Doctrine of which Text can be only this, That no man can have an Authority over other men, who are his Fellow-creatures, except it be derived to him from God, who is the Lord of all; and that whatever Power is derived to any Superiors over Inferiors, it muſt be ſubordinated to God, from whom it was derived: And as the Apoſtle doth infer from the former Aſſertion, That <hi>Every ſoul ſhould be ſubject to, and not reſiſt, this Authority,</hi> even for <hi>Conſcience-ſake,</hi> becauſe derived from God; ſo he infers from the latter, That the Superior, who uſeth this <hi>Authority,</hi> muſt adminiſter it as the Miniſter of God, for the good of men, in protecting Virtue, and diſcouraging Vice, becauſe his Authority is ſubordinated to God, the Supreme and Abſolute Lord of all Mankind.</p>
            <p>And that the Apoſtle doth ſpeak of <hi>Authority</hi> according to its general <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>inſtitution,</hi> and not the <hi>particular perſons</hi> by whom, or <hi>forms</hi> in which it was then exercis'd, is evident from the excellent properties and ends of this <hi>Authority</hi> which he enumerates; which do belong indeed to that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> which God hath inſtituted, but cannot certainly be aſcribed to the Government of <hi>Nero</hi> the preſent, and the worſt of Emperors. And to make this more plain and unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, it may be obſerv'd, that as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Authority</hi> in the general, calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>the <hi>Ordinance of God;</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of the perſons by whom this <hi>Authority</hi> is adminiſtred, calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13, 14.</note> whether it be the <hi>King, as ſupreme, or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Magiſtrates commiſſion'd by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all, I am ready to acknowledg, that the <hi>Law of God</hi> doth ſecure <hi>Princes,</hi> yea, and the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of their <hi>Subjects</hi> in the quiet poſſeſſion of thoſe <hi>Rights</hi> which they have juſtly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd; but the <hi>Rights</hi> themſelves are not founded on a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96317:6"/>but <hi>Humane</hi> Conſtitution; for tho the Law of God doth prohibit us to defraud a <hi>private perſon</hi> of any part of his juſt poſſeſſions, yet we do not think that any <hi>Law of God</hi> did <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently entitle</hi> him to ſuch a poſſeſſion, or doth <hi>neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail</hi> it on his Family; but that his <hi>Right</hi> is grounded on the Laws and Conſtitutions of the Country in which he lives: So, tho <hi>Kings</hi> have the Law of God to maintain and protect them in the uſe of that <hi>Authority</hi> to which they have a <hi>juſt Right;</hi> yet that <hi>Right</hi> is not to be meaſured by any Law of God, but the Conſtitutions of the Realm, and may be acquired or alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated without committing any ſin againſt God, as they who aſſert a <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> would pretend.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another falſe principle to be diſmiſſed, is a wide miſtake of the Nature of that Government under which we live, which aſſerts the <hi>Engliſh Monarchy</hi> to be <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>unlimited,</hi> at leaſt that in its <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Eſſential</hi> Conſtitution it is ſo, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe. We cannot but reflect on the <hi>ill deſign,</hi> or <hi>ill conduct</hi> of ſome who in their Diſcourſes on this Subject, have tranſcribed out of their <hi>common places</hi> all the <hi>great things</hi> which any <hi>Princes</hi> have <hi>aſſerted</hi> to themſelves, or have been <hi>aſcrib'd</hi> to them by ambitions flatterers, or have been <hi>acquir'd</hi> by them in overreaching Compacts, or by a violent force; and have, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>reſtriction</hi> or <hi>exception,</hi> applied them to the <hi>Monarch</hi> of our <hi>Iſland,</hi> as if there could be but one ſort of <hi>Government</hi> in the world, or that <hi>ours</hi> did eminently include all the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that can be conceiv'd in ſpeculation, or can be found to be aſcrib'd to any King or Emperor in any Part, or Age of the World.</p>
            <p>Upon this Principle they have exalted the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch into as <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> a <hi>Sovereign,</hi> as any Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Conſtantineple;</hi> they make his <hi>Will</hi> the ſole ſpring of our Government, from which it is originally deriv'd, and into which it muſt be ultimately reſolved: they allow to an <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> no more power than to give ſome inauthoritative Advice, which the King may uſe or neglect as he thinks fit. They think a <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> whatever it may be with reſpect to <hi>God,</hi> yet with reſpect to the <hi>People,</hi> is only a cuſtomary Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, or inſignificant Formality. They ſuppoſe all legal limitations of the Government to be but the King's arbitrary and temporary Condeſcentions, which he may retract without
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96317:7"/>doing any Injury to the People; and, in a word, that all our Laws are entirely dependent on His Pleaſure for their <hi>Being, Continuance,</hi> and <hi>Influence;</hi> but his <hi>Will</hi> is in all Caſes unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and irreſiſtible. Such Maxims as theſe quite alter the Frame of our <hi>Engliſh Government,</hi> raiſe up our <hi>King</hi> into a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and depreſs his Subjects into Slaves, and ſerve only to render the <hi>King odious,</hi> and his <hi>People miſerable;</hi> and therefore, as no wiſe Man can forbear wiſhing that they may not be true, ſo upon enquiry we ſhall find that they have been advanced either by the <hi>Fondneſs</hi> of ſome, who frame Schemes of <hi>Government</hi> in their own imagination; or by the <hi>Ignorance</hi> of others, who are deceiv'd with the ſound of the aequivocal Name of <hi>King,</hi> or by the <hi>Craft</hi> of thoſe who make a Trade of <hi>advancing</hi> the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their own <hi>Advancement.</hi> Indeed if the preceding Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had proved true, That <hi>Monarchy is a Divine Inſtitution,</hi> it would be neceſſary for us to grant, that no other Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment could be mix'd with it, or <hi>That</hi> be reſtrained by any Limitations, becauſe it cannot be lawful for Man to adulterate or infringe the Ordinance of God: But ſeeing the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> doth not appear, we have reaſon to ſuppoſe that our <hi>Engliſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> is built on the Topical Conſtitutions of this Countrey, and may differ from the Government of other Countreys, as much as our Tempers, Intereſts, and Circumſtances do. For, if the Supreme Governor of the VVorld hath not thought fit to preſcribe <hi>One Form</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> to be every-where obſerved, he hath permitted to every Nation a Liberty of framing to themſelves ſuch a Conſtitution as may be moſt uſeful and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable; and as it is <hi>inconceivable</hi> that all Nations ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire in the ſame Platform of <hi>Governments;</hi> ſo it is moſt <hi>unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> to ſeek in <hi>Judea, Italy,</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> for the Meaſures or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, which was made, and is therefore to be found only <hi>at Home,</hi> and ſhould be deſcrib'd ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from its own <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> than any fine <hi>Notions</hi> we can conceive of what it might or ſhould be. And if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the Government it ſelf, we may eaſily diſcover what its eſſential Forms and Properties are; for ſurely a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that hath been publickly tranſacted through ſo many Ages, and hath made ſo great a Figure in the world, cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main an imperceptible Secret, or an unintelligible Myſtery; and I cannot forbear ſuſpecting thoſe, who diſguiſe it with ſo many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96317:7"/>Uncertainties and Obſcurities, that they deſign to miſlead us into a miſtake of that which they will not allow us to underſtand. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle skill in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory will ſuffice to inform us, That the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> from whom this Nation is chiefly deſcended, did firſt introduce the Form of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and that it was the ſame they had been inur'd to in <hi>Germany;</hi> where, as <hi>Tacitus</hi> obſerves, <hi>Regibus nec infinita aut libera potestas:</hi> Kings <hi>had not an Abſolute or Unlimited Power.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit. de mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. Germ.</hi> Sect. 3, &amp; 5.</note> And from the ancient Records of thoſe early Times we are aſſur'd, That the <hi>Conſent</hi> of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a <hi>Convention</hi> or <hi>Parliament,</hi> did always concur to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Laws;</hi> and alſo their <hi>Conſent</hi> in a <hi>Jury</hi> of Peers was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways admitted in the Execution of <hi>Them:</hi> VVhence the People of <hi>England</hi> have been always acknowledged to be <hi>Free-men.</hi> And tho we read that the <hi>Saxons</hi> were ſubdued by the <hi>Danes,</hi> yet we find not that their Government was changed, but that, after a ſhort Interruption, the Government and Country returned entirely into the Hands of the <hi>Saxons.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> whom we call the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> was <hi>ſuch</hi> only with reſpect to <hi>Harold,</hi> who uſurp'd the Crown, but not with reſpect to the Kingdom, which he claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Succeſſor to King <hi>Edward,</hi> to whom he was related, by whom he was adopted, and from whom he had received a ſolemn Promiſe of the next Reverſion; and accordingly we find, that tho be made ſome external Changes in the Government, yet he made no eſſential Alteration in the Form of it; and the ſame kind of Government hath been tranſmitted by ſucceeding Kings to the preſent Age, with ſome <hi>accidental Improvements,</hi> as our Anceſtors grew wiſer by Experience, or the Neceſſities and intereſts of the Nation did require. Now, inaſmuch as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government was at firſt tranſplanted out of another Countrey, and hath been ripened into a Perfection by ſeveral degrees through a long tract of Time, it would be very <hi>fanciful</hi> to ſuppoſe one ſolemn time when the <hi>Original Compact</hi> between the King and People was firſt made, or to ask after a Book in which it is in a certain Form re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded; that Compact being nothing elſe than a tacit Agreement between the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> to obſerve ſuch common Uſages and Practices, as by an immemorial Preſcription are become the <hi>Common-Law</hi> of our Government. And to underſtand theſe, ſo far as our preſent Caſe requires, there it no neceſſity that ſhould read over all the <hi>Records</hi> in the <hi>Tower,</hi> or all the <hi>Volumes</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Hiſtory,</hi> there being ſeveral ancient <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96317:8"/>us, which fall under eaſie Obſervation, that are ſufficient to inform us of the Nature of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government. For when at a <hi>Coronation</hi> we ſee a <hi>King</hi> preſented to the People, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſolemnly asked and given, what can we reaſonably inſer from thence, but that anciently <hi>Kings</hi> were advanced to their Thrones by the Conſent and Agreement of the People? When we hear the King ſolemnly <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Swear</hi> to maintain to the People their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> to conſerve the <hi>Laws,</hi> and cauſe them to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; muſt we not conclude from thence, that there are <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> reſerved to the People; that the Will of the <hi>King</hi> is limited by the <hi>Law</hi> of the Realm; and that he is bound by <hi>His Oath</hi> to <hi>conſerve</hi> the Laws, as we are by <hi>Ours</hi> to <hi>obſerve</hi> them? When we are taught to call the King our <hi>Leige-Sovereign,</hi> and our ſelves his <hi>Leige-Subjects;</hi> do not thoſe Terms import, that he is bound to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect Us in <hi>All our Rights,</hi> as we are bound to obey Him in <hi>All his Laws?</hi> When we read in the Preamble of every Statute, That it is enacted not only by the Authority of the <hi>King's most Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> but alſo by the Authority of the <hi>Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and of the Commons aſſembled in Parliamen;</hi> is it not very evident from hence, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath a ſhare in the <hi>Legiſlative Power,</hi> which is an eminent Branch of the <hi>Supreme Authority</hi> in this Kingdom? From theſe, and other ſuch eaſie Obſervations, any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial unprejudiced perſon will certainly conclude, that our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Government, according to its <hi>Eſſential Conſtitution,</hi> is a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Three Forms of Government; for he obſerves a <hi>Monarchy</hi> in the <hi>King,</hi> an <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> in the <hi>Peers,</hi> and a <hi>Democracy</hi> in the <hi>Commons;</hi> all which ſhare it <hi>that Part</hi> of the Sovereignty which conſiſts in making Laws. And though our Government be called a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> becauſe That Kind is <hi>predominant</hi> in the Conſtitution, according to the known Rule, That the <hi>Denomination is to be taken from the Excelling Part,</hi> the King having not only a ſhare in the <hi>Nomothetick</hi> Power, but alſo the whole <hi>Executive Power</hi> committed to Him; yet we cannot but conclude, from the foregoing Obſervations, That our <hi>Monarchy</hi> is not <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Unlimited;</hi> that the <hi>Law</hi> is the ſtated Rule and Meaſure of our Government; and that the <hi>Law</hi> cannot be made, altered, or annulled, by the ſole Pleaſure of the King: but as it is the firſt determinate Rule by which the King is to Govern, and the People to Obey, ſo it is to be made or chang'd only by the Conſent of <hi>Both</hi> in a Parliament. I might confirm all this, by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96317:8"/>out of Books ſeveral Teſtimonies which occur in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> in the Writings of <hi>Judges,</hi> and others <hi>Learned</hi> in the <hi>Law:</hi> but as theſe would make a Letter too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo they are unneceſſary to an unprejudic'd Conſiderer, and by others would be ſuſpected of partiality to the People of whom they are a part. I ſhall therefore only add the Teſtimony of King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. who of all men had moſt reaſon to ſtudy, underſtand, and aſſert the Rights of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy. He freely declares, in his <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Nineteen Propoſitions,</hi> p. 96. <q>That there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Three Kinds of Government among Men. <hi>Abſolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, Ariſlocracy,</hi> and <hi>Democracy;</hi> and all theſe having their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Conveniences and Inconveniences: the Experience and Wiſdom of our Anceſtors hath ſo moulded <hi>This</hi> out of a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Theſe,</hi> as to give to this Kingdom (as far as Human Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can provide) the Conveniences of <hi>all Three,</hi> without the Inconveniences of <hi>any One.</hi>
               </q> He alſo, in the ſame Anſwer, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <q>That in this Kingdom the Laws are jointly made by a King, by a Houſe of Peers, and by a Houſe of Commons.</q> He likewiſe affirms in his Declaration from <hi>Newmarket,</hi> 
               <q>That the Law is the Meaſure of his Power.</q> And in another Declaration to the Miniſters and Freeholders of the County of <hi>York,</hi> he acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, "That his Prerogatives are built upon the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>From theſe and other ſuch Paſſages which frequently occur in the Writings of the <hi>King,</hi> who ſo earneſtly diſputed for the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> we may be abundantly convinc'd that the <hi>Engliſh Monarchy</hi> is not <hi>unmixt,</hi> or <hi>unlimited;</hi> and cannot therefore enough admire the lewd preſumption of others, who have dar'd to attempt a change in our <hi>Engliſh Government,</hi> who prefer the extremes of <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> to the juſt <hi>temperament</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution;</hi> who have labour'd to tempt our <hi>Kings</hi> into an affectation of <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>arbitrary Power,</hi> and have miſerably overlay'd the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of their <hi>Fellow-ſubjects</hi> with a <hi>boundleſs unlimited dread</hi> of a <hi>boundleſs unlimited Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There are alſo great miſtakes about the <hi>meaſures</hi> of our <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion,</hi> which are neceſſary to be removed before our Conſciences can make a free and impartial determination of the Caſe before us. We have been told it often, and with great earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that we are bound in Conſcience to yield an <hi>active Obedience</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> in all caſes not countermanded by God, and to reſiſt him in no caſe whatſoever. If indeed the two foregoing Errors had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96317:9"/>ſtood the proof, this would have follow'd by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: for if a <hi>Monarch</hi> be <hi>jure Divino,</hi> he muſt be <hi>abſolute;</hi> and if he be ſo, there is no caſe, not excepted by God, in which we muſt not <hi>obey</hi> him, and none at all in which we may <hi>reſiſt</hi> him; but then we may make this advantage from the connexion which theſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors have one to another, That if one of them be refuted, the reſt much neceſſarily fall with it: and if according to the <hi>Engliſh Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> premis'd, our Government be founded on the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of this Country, and according to thoſe <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> be mixt and limited, then there may be ſome caſes in which it may be lawful for us not to obey the King, and not unlawful to reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>For tho it may be true, that we are bound to <hi>obey actively</hi> whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is commanded by the <hi>Legiſlative Power</hi> of the Kingdom, and is not repugnant to any Law of God; yet we cannot aſſert ſo much with reſpect to the <hi>King only,</hi> becauſe he having not the whole <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power,</hi> an Act of his <hi>private Will</hi> is deſtitute of that <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> which can derive an obligation upon Conſcience: altho therefore a King may require things not <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the Law <hi>of God,</hi> yet if they are beyond that <hi>Authority</hi> which the <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have aſſign'd to him, his Subjects are not bound in <hi>conſcience</hi> to <hi>obey</hi> thoſe <hi>Commands;</hi> and tho in <hi>ſome caſes</hi> they may <hi>comply</hi> by a <hi>voluntary Conceſſion,</hi> yet they are oblig'd to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn</hi> and <hi>withſtand</hi> ſuch proceedings if they increaſe ſo far as to threaten a fatal ſubverſion of the <hi>Government.</hi> But how can we defend our ſelves againſt any exorbitant Acts of the <hi>King</hi>'s pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Will, if diſarm'd and fetter'd by the Doctrines of <hi>paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> and <hi>Nonreſiſtance?</hi> what may not a King do, and a People ſuffer, if no defence may be us'd? I do not here forget to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> God hath requir'd to that <hi>Supreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> which he hath inſtituted, or what <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> we are to pay to thoſe <hi>Governors</hi> who ſuſtain and adminiſter it; nor how <hi>impatient</hi> men ordinarily are of the yoak of <hi>Government,</hi> and how apt to inlarge their <hi>liberty</hi> into <hi>licentiouſneſs;</hi> nor how <hi>pernicious</hi> diſorder and confuſion muſt needs be to any Society; and therefore I uſe the utmoſt Caution I can to ſteer aright amidſt the Rocks on the one hand, and the Sands on the other, that I may not make ſhipwrack of a good Conſcience. I therefore premiſe and ſincerely acknowledg, as I have learn'd from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>Every ſoul muſt be ſubject to the Supreme Authority which God hath inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that if he reſiſt, he is worthy of condemnation:</hi> and according
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96317:9"/>to S. <hi>Jude,</hi> that we muſt not <hi>deſpiſe dominions, or ſpeak evil of dignities;</hi> and that thoſe untameable Spirits which are impatient of Government, are like <hi>wild Beaſts made to be deſtroyed.</hi> I have alſo learn'd from S. <hi>Peter,</hi> to <hi>ſubmit to every ordinance of men for the Lord's ſake, whether to the King as ſupreme, or to Governors ſent by him,</hi> ſo as not to <hi>diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi> or <hi>reſiſt</hi> them in the uſe of that <hi>Authority</hi> which the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the Kingdom have <hi>aſſigned</hi> to them. I have from the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> learned farther to be <hi>ſubject with all fear, not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward:</hi> ſo that if a King in the adminiſtration of his Government ſhould be too <hi>ſparnig</hi> in his <hi>Rewards,</hi> and over <hi>ſevere</hi> in his <hi>Juſtice;</hi> if too hard to be pleas'd, and as hard to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiated, I muſt be contented; if he injure me in my <hi>private intereſts,</hi> I muſt rather <hi>ſubmit</hi> than oppoſe a <hi>private</hi> to a <hi>publick</hi> good; or if the <hi>publick</hi> Affairs of the Kingdom ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain any detriment or miſchief from his Male-adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet if it be ſuch as will conſiſt with the <hi>being</hi> of the Government and the <hi>Safety</hi> of the People, it ſhould rather be born <hi>patiently,</hi> than redreſſed by a <hi>violent</hi> oppoſition. I acknowledge alſo that in all caſes not certain and notorious, the Subject ought to preſume the <hi>Right</hi> to be rather on his <hi>Prince</hi>'s ſide than on his <hi>own</hi> and never to think any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions <hi>intolerable</hi> till they are <hi>evidently</hi> ſuch, or to call for a <hi>violent</hi> redreſs, till they appear otherwiſe <hi>irremediable.</hi> I muſt acknowledge alſo that I can ſee no Right the Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ject hath from the <hi>Law</hi> of God or Man, to uſe any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt a <hi>King</hi> than what is <hi>defenſive,</hi> or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>judicially</hi> againſt him, or to inflict any puniſhment on his Perſon for any defaults of <hi>Government,</hi> becauſe there can be no <hi>Authority</hi> in our Kingdom ſuperior to that with which the King is inveſted. Yet after all theſe conceſſions it muſt be confeſs'd that the <hi>Regal</hi> Power being in its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution <hi>limited,</hi> and in its Exerciſe liable to be <hi>abus'd,</hi> there may ſuch caſes happen wherein a <hi>defenſive reſiſtance</hi> may be not only <hi>lawful,</hi> but a <hi>neceſſary Duty.</hi> And if we may not <hi>lie for God,</hi> much leſs may we do it in <hi>flattery</hi> to any <hi>Man;</hi> and if Subjects may not be defrauded of their <hi>Eſtates,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96317:10"/>no more ſhould they be of their <hi>Liberties,</hi> to prevent their <hi>abuſe</hi> of them. Wherefore to ſpeak out plainly, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly in a caſe wherein <hi>Conſcience</hi> is ſo much concern'd, I muſt add, that we are not bound in Conſcience to yield <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> to the King any farther than that <hi>Regal Authority</hi> extends, which the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of this Kingdom have inveſted him with; and that thoſe <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> do not <hi>impower</hi> him to <hi>treat</hi> his <hi>Subjects</hi> according to his own <hi>private Will,</hi> but according to the <hi>publick</hi> rule of the <hi>Law;</hi> and by conſequence, whatever grievance is <hi>without</hi> or <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>Law,</hi> the Subject is not bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to bear it, with reſpect to the <hi>King</hi> who had no <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> to impoſe it, though he may <hi>be</hi> ſometimes, with reſpect to the publick Peace; and if <hi>Officers</hi> be appointed by the King to <hi>oppreſs</hi> his Subjects <hi>contrary</hi> to Law, their <hi>Commiſſions</hi> being <hi>illegal,</hi> muſt be without <hi>authority:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Subject is not bound in Conſcience to ſubmit to them, but may <hi>reſiſt</hi> their <hi>injuſt aſſaults,</hi> if he cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>evade</hi> them, and do not diſturb the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> by the defence of his <hi>private Intereſts.</hi> And if we may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a caſe <hi>ſo</hi> ſad, as that a King through ill <hi>counſel</hi> or ſome ſtrong <hi>temptation</hi> ſhould be changed from a <hi>Father</hi> into the <hi>Enemy</hi> of his Country; and ſhould with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable obſtinacy ingage himſelf in ſuch <hi>illegal</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, as plainly and inevitably tend to the <hi>Subverſion</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> and the <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of the People; his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in ſuch <hi>unhappy circumſtances</hi> will be <hi>excuſable</hi> before God, if they uſe ſo much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>defenſive reſiſtance</hi> as he hath made neceſſary for preſerving the <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> For if in Nature a People is preſuppoſed to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Rulers are intended by God for the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of a People, and not a People for the pleaſure of their Rulers, it will be moſt reaſonable to infer, that when the End and the Means become inconſiſtent, the End ſhould be preferr'd, and thoſe Means prevented or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, which would deſtroy the End they ſhould promote.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96317:10"/>
            <p>But theſe things are ſo eaſily anticipated by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> of mankind, that there needs no long diſcourſe about them; and they are indeed too <hi>irkſom</hi> to an ingenuous mind to dwell long upon them: and though our <hi>extraordinary caſe</hi> at preſent hath made it <hi>neceſſary</hi> to ſay ſo <hi>much,</hi> yet I hope a like <hi>caſe</hi> will never happen again, to give occaſion to Subjects to conſider ſo <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutely,</hi> the limits of the <hi>Regal</hi> Power, and of their own <hi>ſubmiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Having now reſcued our <hi>Conſciences</hi> from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices of the foregoing <hi>Errors,</hi> we may be capable of making an impartial judgment of the caſe propounded, <hi>Whether we can with a good Conſcience transfer our Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the late to the preſent King? Allegiance</hi> in its pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary general ſenſe ſignifies, being <hi>obliged</hi> or <hi>bound;</hi> in its political ſenſe it imports that kind of <hi>relation</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers a <hi>Subject</hi> to his <hi>Prince,</hi> and by conſequence it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes the <hi>duties</hi> which reſult from that <hi>relation:</hi> And taking the word in its fulleſt latitude, there will ariſe theſe two difficulties to be diſtinctly reſolved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether our <hi>Conſciences</hi> are <hi>diſcharged</hi> from <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>late King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether we can with a good Conſcience transfer our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>preſent King,</hi> though not the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <hi>Heir</hi> of the Crown?</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſolving the former enquiry it will be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to premiſe, that our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to <hi>James</hi> the Second was not to his Perſon <hi>abſolutely,</hi> but <hi>reſpectlively,</hi> as he ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain'd the Character of <hi>King;</hi> and therefore as we ow'd no <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him before he was <hi>King,</hi> ſo neither can we owe him any now, if he <hi>ceaſe</hi> to be ſo; and I think it too plain to need any proof, that it is poſſible that a perſon may ceaſe to be King, though he ſtill ſurvive; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96317:11"/>that a relation ceaſeth when one of its Terms is loſt. If therefore it appears, That <hi>James</hi> the Second doth ceaſe to be our <hi>King,</hi> though he be ſtill alive, our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him will be ſufficiently diſcharged; and that he doth ceaſe to be our <hi>King,</hi> may, I ſuppoſe, be evinc'd from the following Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If <hi>James</hi> the Second did with an <hi>immoveable obſtinacy</hi> ingage himſelf in ſuch <hi>illegal</hi> and <hi>pernicious</hi> deſigns as were <hi>notoriouſly ſubverſive</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>deſtructive</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> he did thereby ceaſe <hi>de jure</hi> to be our King, and our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him is by conſequence diſcharg'd. The Title of <hi>King</hi> includes both an <hi>Office</hi> to be diſcharg'd, and an <hi>Eſtate</hi> to be injoy'd, but the latter is an <hi>appendant</hi> to the former; when therefore he ceaſeth to <hi>govern</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect</hi> his People according to the Laws of this Kingdom, his <hi>Right</hi> muſt ſo far ceaſe to that <hi>Power, Dignity,</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, which were aſſigned to him for that end, except we can imagine ſome things to have a <hi>moral</hi> power of <hi>ſubſiſting,</hi> when the reaſon of them is gone. And as the <hi>Office</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> is directed by the publick rule of the <hi>Law,</hi> ſo the <hi>right</hi> which any perſon can have to the <hi>Regal Eſtate,</hi> muſt be founded on the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the <hi>Realm;</hi> and theſe <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> muſt either inveſt him with an <hi>abſolute Right</hi> irreſpective to his Office, and then he would be an <hi>abſolute Monarch,</hi> which is before diſprov'd; or elſe it muſt be a conditional Right, reſpecting the <hi>Office</hi> he is to diſcharge, and then the <hi>Right</hi> in <hi>Equity</hi> muſt ceaſe, upon the non-performance of the condition: Suppoſing alſo that a Perſon's <hi>Right</hi> to the <hi>Re al</hi> Eſtate be founded on the <hi>Civil Conſtitutions</hi> of our <hi>Government,</hi> if he will ſet himſelf to <hi>ſubvert</hi> thoſe <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> he cannot thereby but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermine</hi> and <hi>Deſtroy</hi> his own <hi>Right</hi> which was <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructed</hi> on them. And if he obſtinately refuſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the <hi>Regal Office</hi> according to the proper fixt rule of the Law, though he ſtill uſurp the title of <hi>King,</hi> yet he is become quite <hi>another thing,</hi> ſuch as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96317:11"/>aſſign no <hi>Authority</hi> to, and to which we are not ſuppoſed to owe any <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and which we cannot <hi>recognize</hi> without becoming <hi>Acceſſaries</hi> to the moſt illegal practices, and deriving on our ſelves the heinous guilt of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to the ruine of the Government and our Selves.</p>
            <p>And as ſuch a determination of the Caſe is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to reaſon, ſo it is moſt agreeable to the antient principles and practices of <hi>England.</hi> By a Law made in King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor</hi>'s time, it is declared,<note place="margin">Quod niſi fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, nec nomen Regis in eo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabit. <hi>Lamb.</hi> de priſcis <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> p. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That if a King doth not perform his Office, he ſhall not retain ſo much as the name of a King.</hi> We read alſo that<note n="*" place="margin">In principio ſecundi Anni Regni ſui cum incorrigibil s ſuperbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitiae eſſet, congregati ſunt Proceres &amp; Populus totius Regni &amp; eun pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ida delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione à Regno unanimi conſenſu omnium expellebant. <hi>Collect.</hi> p. <hi>769. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sigebert</hi> King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons,</hi> being <hi>incorrigibly Proud and Wicked, he was, in the beginning of the ſecond year of his Reign, by the Nobles, and the People of the whole Kingdom aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, upon mature deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eration, and by unanimous conſent of them all, driven out of his Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus alſo <hi>King John</hi> having broken his <hi>Coronation-Oath,</hi> and endeavour'd by many ways to <hi>inſlave</hi> both the <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Realm,</hi> after many applications, and a defenſive War waged by the Barons againſt him, it was at laſt <hi>agreed,</hi> that <hi>if he did again return to his former wicked Courſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inter caetera, de ejus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſo conſenſu, ita convenit, ut ſi idem <hi>Johannes</hi> ad flagitia prima rediret, ipſi Barones ab ejus fidelitate recederent, nunquam ad eum poſtmodum reverſuri. Cum autem ille fecit noviſſima ſua pejora prioribus, illi de communi Regni Conſilio &amp; approbations ipſum Regno indignum judicarunt. <hi>Collect. 1868. &amp;c. Chron. W. Thorn.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Barons ſhould be for ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas'd from all Allegiance to him; and when he afterward relaps'd into the ſame courſes, they in a general Aſſembly with the approbation of all the Realm, adjudg'd him unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be King.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96317:12"/>
            <p>We find alſo that King <hi>Edward</hi> the Second for following Evil Counſel, and refuſing to hearken to good counſel, for his pride arrogance, for breaking his Coronation Oath,<note place="margin">De Conſilio &amp; aſſenſu omnium Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>torum &amp; Baronum &amp; totius Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunitatis Regui amotus eſt à Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Regni. <hi>Apolog. Adami. de Orleton Collect.</hi> p. <hi>2765.</hi>
               </note> for waſting his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and being found incorrigible and paſt all hopes of amendment, was by <hi>advice and aſſent of all the Prelates, Earles and Barons, and of the whole communitie of the Kingdom depos'd from the Government.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Habent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r antiquo Statuto, &amp; de facto non longe retroaciis temporibus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienter, quod dolendum eſt, habito, Si Rex ex maligno con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio quocunquae, vel inepta con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamacia, aut contemptu, ſeu proterva Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſingulari, aut quoviſmodo irregulari fe alienaverit à à populo ſuo, nec voluerit per jura Regni &amp; Statuta ac landabiles Ordinationes, cum ſalubri conſilio Dominorum &amp; Procerum Regni, gubernari &amp; regulari, ſed capitoſe in ſuis inſanis conſiliis propriam Voluntatem ſuam ſingularem proterve exercere, extunc licitum eſt iis, cum communi aſſenſu &amp; conſenſu Populi Regni, ipſum Regem de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egali ſolio abrogare, &amp; propinquiorum aliquem de ſtirpe Regia loco ejus in Regni ſolio ſablimare. <hi>H. Knighton Collect. 2681.</hi>
               </note> I ſhall add only one inſtance more of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, to whom his Parliament ſent Meſſengers to declare to him, among other things, <hi>that they find in an antient Statute, and it hath been done in fact not long ago, that if the King through any evil counſel, or fooliſh contumacy, or out of Scorn, of ſome petulant wilfulneſs, or any other irregular way ſhall alienate himſelf from his people, and ſhall refuſe to be govern'd and guided by the Laws of the Realm, and the Statutes, and laudable Ordinances thereof, together with the wholſome advice of the Lords and great Men of his Realm, but perſiſting headſtrong in his own mad counſels, ſhall petulantly proſecute his own private humour, that then it ſhall be lawfull for them with the common aſſent and conſent of the people of the Realm, to depoſe that ſame King from his Regal Throne, and to ſet up ſome other of Royal Family in his place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The preſent Caſe ſtated.</note>Theſe Teſtimonies
which I met with in a late <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> and which I am aſſur'd from an able hand to be <hi>faithfully</hi> recited, and of an <hi>unſuſpected credit,</hi> I have <hi>abridg'd</hi> and <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rib'd,</hi> to confirm that <hi>truth</hi> on which the <hi>Argument</hi> is built, that according to our <hi>Engliſh Conſtitutions,</hi> a perſon may <hi>forfeit</hi> his <hi>Regal Rights,</hi> and ceaſe <hi>de jure</hi> to be <hi>King;</hi> and that according to the <hi>antient Statutes</hi> and <hi>irreprovable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages</hi> of this Country, the <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96317:12"/>
               <hi>remove</hi> ſuch a perſon from the <hi>Government,</hi> when <hi>neceſſary</hi> to prevent a <hi>general</hi> ruine otherwiſe, <hi>inevitable.</hi> Now that the <hi>late King</hi> had brought matters to ſo great an extremity, as is in the <hi>Argument</hi> ſuppos'd, is evident from many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſo recent and notorious, that it was lately acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by all of us in the lowdeſt Complaints. We ſaw him attempting to ſubvert our Parliaments, by <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tupting</hi> their <hi>Elections</hi> with the meaneſt arts, and uſing his power to <hi>pervert</hi> or <hi>fruſtrate</hi> their counſels. We heard thoſe high ſtrains in which he claim'd an abſolute and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Power, our <hi>Laws</hi> were trampled on in <hi>illegal diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations,</hi> and the moſt <hi>partial Execution;</hi> Some were diſſeiſed of their <hi>Freehold</hi> without a trial, and <hi>levies</hi> of Mony were made <hi>without</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> Law; Our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> which are the beſt of all thoſe intereſts which are ſecured to us by a legal Eſtabliſhment, were ſo boldly threatned and attacked, that we ſeemed to enjoy them but precari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and to be in danger of ſeeing them ſpeedily raviſh'd from us. And when we conſider that the <hi>late King</hi> was <hi>inſtigated</hi> and conducted in theſe exorbitant courſes by the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and the <hi>French King</hi> who have long ſince convinced the World, that they dare to perpetrate any miſchief or wickedneſs that will advance their glory, and promote their intereſts: When alſo we conſider that he proceeded in theſe courſes with ſo <hi>obſtinate</hi> a <hi>reſolution,</hi> that when his <hi>Peers</hi> indeavoured to <hi>raclaim</hi> him by <hi>advice,</hi> they only there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by loſt his <hi>favour</hi> and all their <hi>Preferments;</hi> and when ſome of his <hi>Biſhops petitioned</hi> him in the <hi>humbleſt</hi> manner, they were anſwered only with <hi>fury</hi> and <hi>impriſonment:</hi> When laſtly, we conſider how <hi>far</hi> he had advanc'd in this <hi>way,</hi> that we already began to <hi>deſpair,</hi> and our Enemies to <hi>triumph;</hi> and if our <hi>Glorious Deliverer</hi> had not timely intervened, we might have been, in a few months, paſt all hopes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; We may ſurely upon theſe conſiderations be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to conclude, That <hi>England</hi> could not be in more danger, or any <hi>Prince</hi> lie under juſter exceptions, or a people be more diſoblig'd from their <hi>Allegiance.</hi> There are ſome who ſay, that if the <hi>League</hi> with <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:96317:13"/>of a <hi>young Prince,</hi> the <hi>Murder</hi> of the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Eſſex, &amp;c.</hi> were clearly proved, they ſhould not be able to contain themſelves from renouncing all <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him; But though theſe may perchance be proved in due time, yet if they never are, there is certainly enough and too much beſides to ſatisfie any reaſonable Man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If <hi>James</hi> the Second <hi>deſerted</hi> the Kingdom without any <hi>neceſſity</hi> but what he induced on himſelf, and if he made no proviſion for the adminiſtration of the <hi>Government</hi> in his abſence, but by taking away the publick <hi>Seals</hi> and cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the <hi>Writs</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> deſign'd to obſtruct all regular proceedings; and if alſo he hath put himſelf into the hands of the <hi>French King</hi> the greateſt Enemy of our Religion and Country, <hi>without whom</hi> he cannot <hi>return</hi> to us, and with <hi>whom</hi> he cannot <hi>return</hi> without apparent <hi>ruine</hi> to his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> he doth thereby ceaſe <hi>de facto</hi> to be our <hi>King,</hi> and we become diſcharged from all further <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him. I ſuppoſe few would haeſitate in granting ſuch a concluſion, if the <hi>Late King</hi> had by a <hi>writing</hi> under his <hi>hand</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> ſolemnly <hi>abdicated</hi> the <hi>Government;</hi> but I know not what mighty force there is in a <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Words</hi> for <hi>renouncing</hi> the <hi>Government,</hi> that it may not be as effectually performed by a <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>notorious</hi> fact; or that a <hi>King</hi> may not as well <hi>renounce</hi> his <hi>Crown</hi> by <hi>doing</hi> it, as by <hi>ſaying</hi> it; and it is the thing it ſelf and not the way of <hi>expreſſing</hi> it, which is the ground on which the relation between a <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Subjects</hi> is <hi>diſſolved;</hi> and therefore if a <hi>King</hi> doth actually deſert his People, his Government and their Obedience muſt thereupon <hi>actually</hi> ceaſe. You would perchance eaſily allow the argument, if the King had withdrawn <hi>deliberately</hi> and of <hi>choice,</hi> but it is ſaid that he was rather hurried out of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> by force and fear. It will be therefore neceſſary to relate to you the Hiſtory of that tranſaction, which according to the trueſt account that I can meet with, is this: When the <hi>King</hi> went hence the firſt time, the <hi>Prince</hi> and his <hi>Armie</hi> were at a great diſtance, and a Treatie between them was <hi>pretended,</hi> but he left the City before his <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> could
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96317:13"/>return with an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Demands;</hi>
and it is certain that the Treaty was but a deluſive Pretence, and that his Departure was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd on ſome Days before; for he himſelf declar'd to a Perſon of Credit, that the <hi>Queen</hi> had obtained from him a Solemn <hi>Oath</hi> upon the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> on the <hi>Sunday,</hi> that if the went away for <hi>France</hi> on <hi>Monday,</hi> he would not fail to follow her on <hi>Tueſday:</hi> Which he accordingly attempted, and we are very well aſſur'd, that tho his <hi>Subjects</hi> uſed ſome <hi>Force</hi> to <hi>hinder</hi> his <hi>Flight,</hi> yet they uſed none to <hi>compel</hi> him to it. When he left this <hi>City</hi> the ſecond time, he receiv'd a Meſſage from the <hi>Prince,</hi> which deſir'd him to withdraw ſome few Miles from <hi>London,</hi> leſt the <hi>Army</hi> coming thither, and <hi>Whitehall</hi> being throng'd with <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſome Diſorders might thence ariſe, not conſiſtent with the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> or the <hi>Kings Safety;</hi> but we are ſure that it was altogether of his own <hi>Choice</hi> that he went firſt to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and thence out of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>If you reply that the <hi>late King</hi> being <hi>deſerted</hi> by his Subjects, and expoſed naked to the <hi>Prince's Power,</hi> was brought under a neceſſity of <hi>flying.</hi> I muſt anſwer, that that <hi>Neceſſity</hi> was not <hi>abſolute,</hi> but <hi>conditional:</hi> For the <hi>Prince</hi> (to whom he lately allowed the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of being always <hi>Juſt</hi> to his <hi>Word</hi>) had aſſur'd him in his <hi>Declaration,</hi> that if he would ſuffer the <hi>Grievances</hi> of his People to be redreſs'd in a Free <hi>Parliament,</hi> his <hi>Army</hi> ſhould peaceably depart. And not a few of his <hi>Nobles,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> did earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to comply with thoſe Terms, and ſolemnly <hi>aſſure</hi> him that in ſuch a Compliance, they would faithfully adhere to him. If therefore the <hi>late</hi> King would have return'd to the <hi>Engliſh Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> he need not have left the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> but if he <hi>choſe</hi> rather to <hi>depoſe</hi> and <hi>baniſh</hi> himſelf, than <hi>acknowledg</hi> and <hi>correct</hi> the <hi>Errors</hi> of his <hi>Government,</hi> or let fall thoſe <hi>glorious Projects</hi> of advancing <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> and an <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> we have no Reaſon to think ſuch a <hi>wilful Neceſſity</hi> which he impoſed upon himſelf, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Excuſe for <hi>deſerting</hi> his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but rather to conclude, that if he would rather leave us, than leave off to oppreſs us, we are happily releas'd from our <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> together. Yet if we ſhould impute his <hi>Flight</hi> rather to the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of his <hi>Fear,</hi> than to the <hi>obſtinacy</hi> of his <hi>Reſolution;</hi> I do not ſee how the ſame Concluſion can be avoided. For if he leave off to adminiſter the <hi>Government</hi> himſelf, and rather <hi>hinder</hi> than <hi>promote</hi> its <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> by <hi>others,</hi> the courſe of the <hi>Government</hi> is thereby <hi>ſtop'd,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96317:14"/>and either this Nation muſt <hi>disband</hi> into
<hi>Confuſion,</hi> or we are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to ſeek out and imploy ſome other <hi>Expedient.</hi> If you think that he might in ſhort time <hi>overcome his Fears,</hi> and <hi>return</hi> to his <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> even this <hi>Hope</hi> is fatally precluded, by his making himſelf a <hi>Royal Priſoner</hi> to the <hi>French King,</hi> from whom he can expect only, to be <hi>uſed</hi> and <hi>managed</hi> as will moſt contribute to the <hi>Deſigns and Intereſts</hi> of that Haughty <hi>Monarch;</hi> inſomuch that we cannot conceive his <hi>Return poſſible,</hi> without the <hi>Conſent</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of <hi>Him</hi> whom he hath made his <hi>Patron,</hi> and without the dreadful attendance of a <hi>French Army,</hi> and the diſmal Conſequence of utter Ruine to our Church and Nation. And ſurely that <hi>Prince</hi> who can forſake his People, and abandon them out of his Care, and make it impoſſible to return, except as an Enemy to vanquiſh and deſtroy them, may very well be thought to ceaſe <hi>de facto</hi> to be a <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Subjects</hi> to owe any <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It the <hi>Lords Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> and the <hi>Commons</hi>
of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in the late <hi>Convention,</hi> have upon mature Deliberation reſolved and declared, that <hi>James</hi> the 2d hath <hi>abdicated</hi> the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>vacated</hi> the <hi>Throne;</hi> we may be ſatisfactorily confirm'd from their <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> that he ceaſeth to be our <hi>King,</hi> and we to be his <hi>Subjects.</hi> That they have fully and expreſly aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much, I need not prove; and their Teſtimony is ſo <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>anthentick</hi> in die preſent caſe, that we may with good Reaſon ſuffer our ſelves to be concluded by it. For the matter of the Enquiry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of ſeveral ancient Laws and cuſtomary Uſages of this Kingdom, of which the two Houſes are the moſt competent <hi>Judges;</hi> and they repreſenting the whole Nation, and being by our <hi>Choice</hi> commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd to <hi>conſider</hi> and <hi>determine</hi> this <hi>Caſe</hi> for us, we cannot with any <hi>Modeſty</hi> or <hi>Equity reject</hi> their <hi>Determination.</hi> If alſo we conſider, that in all Caſes of a like Nature, the <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by their Repreſentatives, have <hi>uſually</hi> and <hi>finally</hi> determin'd them; and that upon the late King's withdrawing, the chief Power of the Nation could reſide no where rather than in the two Houſes, it ſeems according to our <hi>Engliſh Conſtitutions,</hi> to be the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>private</hi> Men to ſubmit to ſuch a <hi>publick</hi> Judgment. And indeed, if ſuch a ſolemn <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of the three <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> after a long and ſerious <hi>Conſultation</hi> upon the Caſe, ſhall not be thought ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to <hi>determine</hi> it, I wonder who can, or may do it? For as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons are leſs capable of making ſo exact a Judgment, ſo if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96317:14"/>every one ſhould undertake to decide it, we muſt be reduc'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by into a helpleſs ſtate of utter Confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The other Difficulty in the preſent Caſe to be conſider'd, is, Whether we may <hi>lawfully</hi> transfer our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the preſent <hi>King,</hi> he being not the <hi>next immediate Heir?</hi> I may here preſuppoſe that our <hi>preſent King</hi> is <hi>acknowledged</hi> by the <hi>World</hi> to be ſo eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indued with all <hi>Royal Virtues</hi> and <hi>Abilities,</hi> and to have obliged the <hi>Gratitude</hi> of this <hi>Nation</hi> with ſo <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> a Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; that every <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>good</hi> Man among us cannot but be ready to addreſs an hearty <hi>Allegiance</hi> to him, if it can appear <hi>lawful</hi> for him to do ſo; and where the <hi>Heart</hi> is ſo well inclined, it will not be difficult to convince the <hi>Judgment,</hi> if we conſider theſe few Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That according to our <hi>Engliſh Conſtitutions</hi> it is not neceſſary that the next <hi>immediate Heir</hi> ſhould ſucceed. For if we review in <hi>Hiſtory</hi> the ancient <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of our Country, which are the <hi>Common Law</hi> of our <hi>Government,</hi> we ſhall find, that, tho the <hi>Crown</hi> hath been uſually appropriated to the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> and in that Latitude is ſaid to be Hereditary; yet it hath very frequently paſſed over the next <hi>Heir</hi> to ſome other Branch of the Family, which was thought more capable of promoting the publick Ends of the <hi>Government</hi> in its preſent Circumſtances: And we find no pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cenſure ever paſſed upon ſuch a King, or his <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> in the leaſt diſabled thereby. And to make this matter unqueſtionably <hi>evident</hi> to any Man who is not far gone in the <hi>Conceit,</hi> that the <hi>Inheritance</hi> or <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> is <hi>Jure divine,</hi> I add that the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have been allow'd by die whole <hi>Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power</hi> of this Nation to diſpoſe of the Crown by their Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which, as it <hi>may</hi> ſuppoſe that they would not give it out of the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> ſo it <hi>muſt</hi> ſuppoſe that it was not neceſſary it ſhould deſcend to the immediate <hi>Heir;</hi> for he being determined by <hi>Nature,</hi> could receive no Advantage from ſuch a Nomination. Thus particularly it was allow'd to <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and he, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute in that behalf, ſetled the Crown on his Son <hi>Edward,</hi> and the Remainder on his Daughters <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> both which could not be Heir: And we find it alſo enacted in the 13th of <hi>Eliz.</hi> that whoever ſhould maintain in her Time that <hi>ſhe</hi> and her. <hi>Parliament</hi> might not limit the Deſcent of the Crown, ſhould incur the Guilt of High-Treaſon, and after her Life, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96317:15"/>Forfeiture of his Goods. From which Authentick Teſtimonies we cannot conclude leſs, than that it is not neceſſary that the neat <hi>immediate Heir</hi> ſhould always ſucceed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider that our <hi>Allegiance</hi> being removed from the late <hi>King,</hi> it muſt be referr'd to ſome other Perſon, and we can think of none for whoſe ſake we may juſtly deny it to the preſent King. The pretended <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> lying under ſuch a general and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement ſuſpicion of being an Impoſtor, and being at preſent under the Conduct and diſpoſal of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> we ſee in him more Reaſons to <hi>diſſuade</hi> than <hi>invite</hi> our <hi>Allegiance.</hi> Our preſent <hi>Queen,</hi> who is the next <hi>immediate Heir,</hi> is not pretermitted; and tho ſhe hath a <hi>Conſort</hi> in the Royal Dignity, yet he is ſuch as was by <hi>Marriage</hi> become out with her, and who was admitted to the <hi>Partnerſhip,</hi> not without her <hi>Advice</hi> and <hi>Conſent.</hi> And the <hi>King</hi> himſelf being a Branch of the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> not far removed in the Succeſſion, and who by the late <hi>glorious Enterprize</hi> hath retrieved the <hi>Right</hi> of both the <hi>Royal Siſters,</hi> and ſecured the <hi>Government</hi> it ſelf from <hi>Subverſion,</hi> it cannot but ſeem very <hi>indecent</hi> and <hi>unjuſt</hi> to <hi>overlook</hi> him in our <hi>Allegiance.</hi> If, laſtly, we conſider that the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and the <hi>Civil</hi> Intereſts of our own <hi>Nation,</hi> and of ſome of our beſt <hi>Neighbours</hi> are at preſent in moſt <hi>imminent</hi> and <hi>extraordinary</hi> Danger, which in Human Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility is not to be <hi>avoided</hi> but by the <hi>Proweſs</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of this <hi>Illuſtrious Prince,</hi> whom God hath by a <hi>Special Providence</hi> raiſed up among us; we cannot but conclude, that the <hi>Series</hi> of <hi>Providence,</hi> and the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Affairs,</hi> have determin'd our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to His <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and that they ſeem to be unreaſonably nice, who can ſacrifice ſuch <hi>great Intereſts</hi> to an <hi>empty Formality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The great Council of the Nation having <hi>actually</hi> inveſted our <hi>King</hi> with the <hi>Royal Dignity,</hi> he hath thereby a <hi>Right</hi> to our <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance,</hi> and according to the <hi>Laws</hi> of this <hi>Realm,</hi> we become <hi>puniſhable</hi> in refuſing it, and are <hi>indemnified</hi> in performing it, altho his antecedent Title to the <hi>Crown</hi> may not be ſuch as to exclude all Exception. So great to <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>State</hi> as this can be fit to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided only by the Wiſdom of the Nation in the moſt Solemn <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly;</hi> and when ſo decided, <hi>ought</hi> to be ſubmitted to by all <hi>private Perſons,</hi> or all <hi>Settlement</hi> muſt be an <hi>impracticable</hi> thing: and if our <hi>Laws</hi> ſhould not be <hi>executed</hi> according to ſuch an <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick</hi> Determination, the <hi>Government</hi> ſeems to be at a ſtop, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96317:15"/>all hopes of reviving into Motion. I wiſh that they who <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend</hi> or <hi>perplex</hi> their <hi>Conſciences</hi> about ſuch Affairs, would conſider ſeriouſly whether they are <hi>proper</hi> or <hi>capable Judges</hi> of ſuch Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and whether their <hi>Conſciences</hi> may, not be better <hi>conducted</hi> by the Reſolution of <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>are;</hi> whether they behave themſelves as becomes <hi>private Perſons,</hi> who <hi>oppoſe</hi> their <hi>Sentiments</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the <hi>publick Judgment,</hi> or whether any <hi>Government</hi> can ſubſiſt if ſuch a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption</hi> be not reſtrained? For my own part I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that in all <hi>Civil</hi> Caſes, decided by their <hi>proper Judges,</hi> my Conſcience ought to acquieſce, and if I may be thereby miſled into any <hi>Error,</hi> it will be without <hi>Guilt</hi> before God. And I am alſo <hi>inform'd</hi> that by a Statute made 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. we are legally <hi>indemnified</hi> in paying our <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> in <hi>being;</hi> it we continue <hi>faithful</hi> therein, however infirm his Title may after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards appear; and therefore I cannot ſee what <hi>Danger</hi> can <hi>affright</hi> us from our <hi>Allegiance,</hi> or with what <hi>Safety</hi> we can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I have now given you my <hi>Reſolution</hi> of the chief <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties</hi> in the Caſe propounded, and the <hi>Reaſons</hi> on which it is built; and I can think of nothing more requiſite to your Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, except to ſhew how this <hi>Reſolution</hi> doth conſiſt with all the Obligations which may affect a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> in the preſent Caſe; which are, I ſuppoſe, chiefly theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> the Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that <hi>Holy Religion</hi> we profeſs; the Solemn <hi>Oaths</hi> we have taken, or the <hi>Declaration</hi> we have ſubſcribed; and the avowed <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of this <hi>Church</hi> in whoſe Communion we live.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the firſt. The <hi>Rule</hi> of our <hi>Religion</hi> being the Holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> nothing can be <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with one, which is not <hi>repugnant</hi> to the other; and according to the beſt of my Underſtanding, the principles I have proceeded upon, do not diſagree with any Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Text, rightly interpreted. The firſt King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> we meet with in the Old Teſtament is <hi>Saul,</hi> who was advanc'd to the Throne as well by God's <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> as the Peoples <hi>Election,</hi> and who was according to the Peoples deſire, an <hi>abſolute Monarch,</hi> like the other <hi>Kings</hi> in thoſe <hi>Eaſtern Countries:</hi> But this, thanks be to God, is not our Caſe, who live under a <hi>mixt Government,</hi> and a <hi>Monarchy</hi> limited by the fundamental Conſtitutions of this Realm. And yet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96317:16"/>I cannot but obſerve how <hi>David</hi> (who is uſually preſcribed as an eminent Pattern of Loyalty) thought it lawful to raiſe a band of Souldiers for a <hi>defenſive Reſiſtance</hi> againſt the <hi>unjuſt Perſecutions</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> tho an <hi>abſolute Prince;</hi> and ſurely we may conclude a <hi>minori ad majus,</hi> that ſuch a <hi>defenſive Reſiſtance</hi> cannot be leſs <hi>lawful,</hi> when apparently <hi>neceſſary</hi> to preſerve a <hi>whole People</hi> from <hi>imminent</hi> Ruine. I remember our Lord's determination, that his <hi>Kingdom is not of this World:</hi> and as I think We rightly infer from thence, that there is no <hi>ſecular Force</hi> belonging to his <hi>Kingdom</hi> for <hi>inlarging</hi> it's Borders, or <hi>ſecuring</hi> its Intereſlts; ſo I can ſee nothing in theſe words to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but that when any of the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of this World is become the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by incorporating his Religion among its civil Conſtitutions, then we may uſe any Expedients for the defence of our <hi>Religion</hi> which we might uſe in defending any other <hi>Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodges</hi> of our <hi>Civil</hi> Eſtabliſhment. Our Lord hath taught us, <hi>to render unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſar<hi>'s;</hi> and his Apoſtle, that <hi>we muſt render to all Men their Dues, Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom, Fear to whom Fear, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to whom Honour;</hi> but they have leſt us to the Conſtitutions of our Country to determine, what the things of <hi>Ceſar</hi> are, what <hi>Cuſtom</hi> and <hi>Tribute</hi> is due, and when to be paid. I have already had occaſion to conſider the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> concerning our duty of Submiſſion to the <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> and to thoſe who adminiſter it; And upon the general review of the whole, he ſeems to me to do the part of a <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> as well as of a <hi>good Engliſhman,</hi> who hath on his Mind an awful regard: for the <hi>Supreme Authority</hi> which is op divine Inſtitution, who will not refuſe an <hi>Active Obedience</hi> to the Laws of our Legiſlators, if conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent with the Laws of God; who can readily ſubmit to the <hi>King,</hi> and to thoſe that are <hi>commiſſion'd</hi> by him, in the <hi>Execution</hi> of thoſe <hi>Laws;</hi> who pays the higheſt <hi>Civil Honour</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> as the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> who makes the moſt candid and honourable Conſtructions he can of all his <hi>Princes</hi> Actions; who can quietly ſubmit to any acts of Government, tho they ſeem very unjuſt and grievous to his private Intereſtes; and who never thinks a <hi>defenſive Reſiſtance</hi> lawful but when apparently <hi>neceſſary</hi> to ſave a <hi>Kingdom</hi> from utter Ruin. He that can do all this, is a good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in his <hi>Religion,</hi> for he will find it not very eaſy to Fleſh and Blood to go ſo far. But they who are not content with any Notion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96317:16"/>of Religion which will not expoſe to ruin the Kingdom that embraceth it, do but <hi>traduces</hi> our holy <hi>Religion,</hi> and expoſe it to the <hi>Contempt</hi> and <hi>Hatred</hi> of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us next conſider how the <hi>Reſolution.</hi> I have given, will conſiſt with the <hi>Oaths</hi> we have taken, and the <hi>Declaration</hi> we have Subſcribed. You will here give me leave to premiſe that the <hi>Forms</hi> we have <hi>ſworn</hi> or ſubſcrib'd, are not to be taken careleſly according to the <hi>meer ſound</hi> of words, but are to be underſtood according to the <hi>Senſe</hi> which they plainly expreſs, and which appears to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by our <hi>Superiors</hi> in impaſing them. And if we conſider our <hi>Oaths</hi> and Declaration according to this <hi>Rule,</hi> we ſhall diſcover that they have brought upon us no new degree of <hi>Allegiance</hi> or <hi>Subjection,</hi> which was not always due according to the ancient Fundamental Conſtitutions of this Kingdom; that we have hereby loſt none of our Engliſh Rights and Liberties; nor the <hi>King</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd his <hi>Prerogative</hi> beyond what it always was and ought to be; and therefore if according to the ancient <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> the Government is mixt and the Monarchy <hi>limited,</hi> ſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues. If the Freemen of <hi>England</hi> were before theſe <hi>Oaths</hi> bound to no <hi>Active</hi> or <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience beyond what the Law of the Land preſcribes, they arc bound to no more ſince; and if it was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>lawful</hi> for the People of <hi>England</hi> in an extreme neceſſity, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move a <hi>King</hi> whoſe <hi>Government</hi> was became inconſiſtent with the Publick-Weal, and to ſet up another by whom the publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt may be ſecur'd, it is as <hi>lawful</hi> ſtill notwithſtanding theſe <hi>Oaths</hi> we have taken, or the <hi>Declaration</hi> we have ſubſcribed. And to evince this more ſatisfactorily, let us deſcend to Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> preſcribed 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> doth plainly appear from the <hi>Preamble</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Act,</hi> and from all the parts of the <hi>Oath</hi> it ſelf, to be intended only for aſſerting to the Queen a <hi>Supremacy</hi> over <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Perſons, and in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Cauſes, in oppoſition to the pretentions of the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> When therefore it ſpeaks of bearing <hi>Faith</hi> and true <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> to the <hi>Queen,</hi> and her <hi>Heirs,</hi> and lawful <hi>Suceſſors,</hi> it is in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition to all <hi>Foreign</hi> Juriſdictions, Powers, Superiorities and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities; and when it ſpeaks of our aſſiſting and defending her <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Preheminencies</hi> and <hi>Authorities,</hi> it is only of ſuch as have been <hi>granted</hi> or <hi>belonging,</hi> or <hi>united</hi> and <hi>annexed</hi> to the Imperial <hi>Crown</hi> of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96317:17"/>this <hi>Realm:</hi> And that no new Power was hereby given to the <hi>Queen</hi> is evident, for when ſhe was inform'd that this was by ſome preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhe cauſed a Paper to be printed, called <hi>An Admonition to ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Men deceived by the Malicious,</hi> in which ſhe declares, <q>That ſhe would have all her loving Subjects underſtand, that nothing was, is, or ſhall be meant, or intended by the ſame Oath, to have any other Duty, Allegiance or Bond required by the ſame Oath, than was acknowledg'd to be due to <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. — and that her Majeſty neither doth nor ever will challenge any other <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> than what was challeng'd and lately uſed by the ſaid Noble King of Famous Memory, which is and was of ancient Times due to the Imperial Crown of this Realm; that is, under God to have the Sovereignty and Rule over all manner of Perſons born within theſe Realms, Dominions and Countries, of what Eſtate either Eccleſiaſtical or Temporal ſoever they be; ſo as no other Foreign Power ſhall or ought to have any Superiority over them.</q> And to render this Expoſition of the <hi>Queen</hi> more Authentick, we find it confirm'd by an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> wherein is this <hi>Proviſo;</hi> 
               <q>Provided alſo, That the Oath expreſſed in the ſaid <hi>Act,</hi> made in the ſaid Firſt Year, ſhall be taken and expounded in ſuch Form, as is ſet forth in an Admonition annexed to the <hi>Queen's Majeſties</hi> Injunctions, publiſhed in the Firſt Year of her Majeſties Reign; That is to ſay, to confeſs and acknowledg in her Majeſty, her Heirs and Succeſſors, none other Authority than that was challenged and lately uſed by the Noble King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. as in the ſaid Admonition more plainly may appear.</q> I think we may be abundantly ſatisfied from ſo expreſs a Teſtimony both of the <hi>Queen</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> that the Oath of <hi>Supremacy</hi> hath aſſerted no <hi>new Power</hi> to the Crown, nor deriv'd any <hi>new Allegiance</hi> on the Subject, but hath only ingaged him to pay that Fealty, which an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> did always owe to his Prince; and if that be all, it doth no way contradict the Poſitions above aſſerted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> appointed by an Act. 3. <hi>Jacob.</hi> 1. doth manifeſtly appear in the Body of the Act, and of the Oath it ſelf, to be intended, not for making any new <hi>kind</hi> or <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> but only for aſſerting the old <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> of an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> againſt the novel Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, of the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which pretended to a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96317:17"/>power of <hi>Excommunicating</hi> and <hi>Depoſing</hi> Kings, and of <hi>releaſing</hi> Subjects from their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and of <hi>bestowing</hi> this Kingdome on ſome other <hi>Prince</hi> ac the <hi>Popes</hi> pleaſure. And that this <hi>Oath was</hi> intended only to aſſert our <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance</hi> in oppoſition to ſuch <hi>Popiſh</hi> pretences, is evident from hence, that the <hi>Oath</hi> was at firſt <hi>appointed,</hi> and for ſome years was requir'd, <hi>only</hi> of <hi>known or ſuſpeted Papiſts.</hi> And an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> following 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Jac.</hi> I. declares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this <hi>Oath,</hi> that it is <hi>limited and preſcribed, tending only to the Declaration of ſuch Duty, as every true and well aſſected Subject, not only by bond of Allegiance, but alſo by the Commandment of Almighty God, ought to bear to the King his Heirs and Succeſſors.</hi> We find alſo that King <hi>James</hi> doth profeſſedly aſſert and defend no more in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for this Oath, and in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cited, that <hi>Apology</hi> is approv'd and commended: And it being in that very <hi>Act</hi> requir'd that this <hi>Oath</hi> ſhould be <hi>Adminiſtred</hi> not only to <hi>Papists,</hi> but alſo to all others his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects, we cannot conceive that our Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors <hi>underſtood,</hi> or <hi>intended</hi> it in any other, than that <hi>limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and <hi>preſcribed</hi> ſenſe they had before acknowledged. From hence therefore we may infer, that this <hi>Oath</hi> doth ſecure the <hi>King</hi> againſt all <hi>Popiſh pretenſions,</hi> but not againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> conſtitutions; and that the <hi>Allegiance</hi> we have ſworn is no more than was <hi>antecedently neceſſary</hi> from thoſe conſtotutions, and by conſequence that if according to thoſe <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> a King may be <hi>removed</hi> from the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemment,</hi> and his people be <hi>releaſed</hi> from their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> ſo they may be ſtill, notwithſtanding any thing <hi>expreſs'd,</hi> or <hi>intended</hi> in the Form of this Oath. But now if ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us (which I fear is the caſe of many) do miſtake the matter of this Oath, and think they have Sworn to another <hi>kind,</hi> or higher <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> than our Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators intended, they cannot but thereby <hi>inthral</hi> their <hi>Conſciences</hi> with great perplexities; and can no other way find Eaſe, than by ſtating the <hi>Obligation</hi> of their <hi>Oath,</hi> according to the intention of thoſe Superiours who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd it; and this may relieve them, for I ſuppoſe that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96317:18"/>tho' a Man may thro' miſtake ſuppoſe his Obligation to be greater than it is, yet that a <hi>promiſſory Oath</hi> doth real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblige him no farther, than the party by whom the form or his <hi>Oath</hi> was preſcribed, and he to whom it was made, may be reaſonably ſuppos'd to intend and require. Thus for inſtance, if a Man thinks he hath ſworn <hi>Allege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> to the <hi>perſon</hi> of him that is <hi>King,</hi> ſo as to be bound to him, whether he Adminiſter the <hi>Engliſh Government,</hi> or ſet up another quite <hi>contrary</hi> to it; or that it obligeth him to obey the Acts of a <hi>Kings private Will,</hi> tho' without and contrary to <hi>Law;</hi> or that his <hi>Allegiance</hi> is not <hi>termi nable</hi> but by death, altho' the perſon to whom he Swore, may long before ceaſe <hi>de jure,</hi> or <hi>de facto</hi> to be <hi>King;</hi> and to mention only one caſe more, which I obſerve to be ſomewhat common, if any thinks, he hath ſworn ſuch an <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>Kings Heirs,</hi> and <hi>lawful Succeſſors,</hi> as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth him in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to find out who is the <hi>next imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Heir,</hi> to aſſiſt him in acquiring the Crown, and to pay ſubjection to him and to no other; altho' the great <hi>Council,</hi> or the whole <hi>Legiſlative power</hi> of the Nation ſhould ſee reaſonto determine otherwiſe; In theſe and other ſuch Caſes, it is plain that our <hi>Conſciences</hi> are intangled, not with the <hi>real Obligations</hi> which are upon them, but with our <hi>miſtakes</hi> about them; that we conceit an <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> which our Anceſtors never knew, and our <hi>Engliſh Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> do not require or allow.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Declaration</hi> we have ſubſcribed according to the Act in 14 C. 2. is in theſe Words, <hi>That it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever to take Arms against the King; and that I do abhor that traiterous poſition, of taking Arms by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion'd by him.</hi> Which <hi>Declaration</hi> may be conſider'd, in the preſent caſe, either as it expreſſeth our <hi>own</hi> judgment, or as it expreſſeth the judgment of our <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> who requir'd it. As it is <hi>our Declaration,</hi> it can only import, that when we ſubſcrib'd it, our judgment was really ſuch, as we then thought this form of words did properly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, but we did not hereby declare that we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96317:18"/>change that judgment, if convinc'd by ſufficent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and therefore cannot be? bound in <hi>Conſcience</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to think, or act contrary to that <hi>Declaration.</hi> But an Argument from this <hi>Declaration</hi> is of more force as it pleads the judgment and determination of our <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> which will therefore deſerve to be more attentively conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd. I acknowledg that this <hi>Form</hi> was intended, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the <hi>Rebellious principles</hi> and <hi>practices</hi> of the times immediately preceding, and muſt conclude that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the judgment of this <hi>Parliament, King Charles</hi> the I. did never <hi>de jure</hi> fall from his <hi>Regal Right,</hi> and that conſequently the War his Subjects wag'd againſt him was a <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and the <hi>poſitions</hi> on which they proceeded were <hi>traiterous;</hi> and that it is not lawful upon pretence of his <hi>Authority,</hi> or any other pretence whatſoever to take Arms againſt his perſon, who continues to be <hi>de jure King:</hi> In all which the Parliament doth declare no <hi>defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Reſiſtance</hi> to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> which was not <hi>always</hi> ſo, nor condemn any <hi>poſitions</hi> which are not in themſelves an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently <hi>traiterous;</hi> and whoever thinks that they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded more, muſt ſuppoſe that that <hi>Parliament</hi> alter'd the Conſtitutions of our <hi>Engliſh Government,</hi> and did by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent conſequence, expoſe the Nation to utter Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And if any of us in ſubſcribing the Declaration, had any other apprehenſions of it; we may, and I think we ſhould renounce and condemn them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us in the laſt place conſider how this reſolution will agree with the received <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> We need not, I know, profeſs ſo high a regard for our <hi>Church,</hi> as to think any doctrine upon her ſole <hi>Authority,</hi> to be a Sufficient rule of our <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and yet it cannot misbecome us to pay ſo great a deference to he Judgment, as never to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it without great <hi>regret.</hi> But upon ſecond thoughts I find we ſhall be under no neceſſity of doing ſo; for tho there have been for ſome time, a <hi>party</hi> among us who have appropriated to themſelves the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> excluſive of their brethren; yet if we extend her
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96317:19"/>Arms wide enough to embrace all her <hi>genuine</hi> children ſince the Reformation, we ſhall find enough on our ſide to juſtifie <hi>our doctrines</hi> to be conſiſtent with her <hi>principles.</hi> Her Homilies no where, that I know of, aſſert the Errors I have here condemned, or condemn any of the poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I have here aſſerted. The Homilies of <hi>Obedience</hi> teach us to <hi>Submit to lawful Authority and to know our bounden duties to common Authority,</hi> but they teach us no <hi>loyalty,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide or contrary to law. The Homilies. againſt Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion are particularly deſigned againſt the Papiſts, whoſe Rebellion was the occaſion upon which they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and tho they teach us not to reſiſt our Prince if his Government be <hi>legal,</hi> however contrary to our <hi>Religion</hi> or any other intereſts, yet they no where forbid, a defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive reſiſtance againſt <hi>illegal</hi> oppreſſions which threaten an inevitable ruin to our Country;<note place="margin">Hom. of Obed. pag. 75.</note> for they deſcribe the Rebellion they condemn to be no other then, reſiſting or withſtanding common Authority. And that the principles of loyalty which obtained in the Church at that time were no other then I have been now aſſerting, we may eaſily ſatisfie our ſelves from that form of <hi>Prayer</hi> they are charged with by the Parliament, in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> reign, <hi>that God would turn her heart from Idolatry to the true Faith, or elſe ſhorten her dayes and take her quickly out of the way:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sr. Simon D'-Ewes journall p. 207.</note> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from tne Reaſons which the Biſhops preſented to <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> to prove that ſhe ought to take away the life of <hi>Mary Queen</hi> of <hi>Scots</hi> becauſe an Enemy to their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> tho the next Heireſs of the Crown; as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did of <hi>Licinius</hi> his fellow <hi>Emperour</hi> becauſe he was an Enemy of the <hi>Empire</hi> and of the Chriſtan Religion; And to ſuch as might object againſt their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and advice they thus replie, <hi>If our danger be joyn'd with the danger of our Gracious Soveraign and natural Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, we ſee not how we can be accounted godly Biſhops or faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects if in common peril we ſhould not cry out &amp; give warning: Or on the other hand how they can be thought to have true hearts toward God and toward their Prince and Country that will miſlike our ſo doing, and ſeek thereby to diſcredit us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96317:19"/>
            <p>We may alſo know their principles in the preſent caſe from the <hi>Subſidies</hi> which the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ergy</hi> gave to the <hi>Queen</hi> in <hi>ſeveral</hi> Convocations in the fifth, thirty fifth, and forty third years of her Reign, for her maintaining and aſſiſting the <hi>Scotch, French,</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> in their defence of their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> againſt the injuſt oppreſſions of their Princes, as may be collected out of the preambles of thoſe Subſidy Acts. And if it were not too tedious, this might be fully atteſted out of the writings of ſuch Biſhops as were moſt eminent in thoſe times.</p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Def. of Apol. p. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Melancthon &amp;c.</hi> hath theſe words <hi>They do not teach the people to rebel againſt their Prince, but only to defend themſelves by all lawful means a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt oppreſſion; as did David againſt King Saul, and ſo do the Nobles in France at this day. They ſeek not to kill, but to ſave their own lives, as they have openly proteſted by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick writing to the world.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> in his book of the <hi>true difference between Chriſtian ſubjection</hi> and <hi>Unchriſtan Rebellion,</hi> dedicated to <hi>Queen Elizaheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 520. <hi>Edit.</hi> 1585.</note> thus gives his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning that defenſive Reſiſtance which the <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots</hi> uſed againſt the injuſt oppreſſions of their King. <hi>I will not,</hi> Saith he, <hi>raſhly pronounce all that reſiſt to be Rebels: Caſes may fall out in Chriſtian Kingdoms, where the people may plead their Right againſt the Prince and not be charged with Rebellion. As for example, if a Prince ſhould go about to ſubject his Kingdom to a forreign Realm, or change the form of the Comonwealth from Empire to Tyranny, or neglect the Laws establiſhed by common conſent of Prince and People, to execute his own pleaſure: In theſe and other caſes, which might be named, if the Nobles and Commons joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to defend their Ancient and accustomed Liberty, Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Laws, they may not well be counted Rebels.</hi> In the next Reign,<note place="margin">In hoc cauſa eorum a Veteris Eccleſiae ratione diſtinguenda eſt <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dem. Anti. c. <hi>17.</hi> p. <hi>91. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> we have the judgment of <hi>Abbot</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> that <hi>the Caſe of the Primitive Chriſtians and of us differs in this, that they had no legal Right for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but were ſubject to the meer pleaſure of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And while it was ſo, Chriſtians did ſuffer themſelves to be kill'd, and kill'd none in their own defence; but when under</hi> Conſtantine <hi>the Emperour they had the Laws on their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96317:20"/>ſide,</hi> [Non tam caedebantur quam caedebant] <hi>they did not ſo much yield up themſelves to be kill'd, as allow themſelves to kill others in their just defence.</hi> Such were the principles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Reign of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and King <hi>James;</hi> but indeed in the next Reign, when <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Councils found admiſſion at our Court, then aroſe <hi>together</hi> the New Principles of <hi>ſupercon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> in the Church, and of <hi>Super Loyalty</hi> in the State; which like a preternatural ferment, have ever ſince di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd the peace of both, and muſt be again caſt out, if we ever recover a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Temper, or a peaceful ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement. If then we frame our Character of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> from the firſt and pureſt half of her Age, before ſhe was ſecretly practis'd upon, by the Arts of her ſubtle Adverſary, we ſhall eaſily diſcover, that her principles of <hi>Conformity</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> are far more <hi>moderate</hi> and <hi>intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> than thoſe, which ſince that time, have been moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly and impetuouſly recommended under her <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable</hi> Name. And I wiſh that every one who profeſſeth an Honourable and kind regard for our <hi>Church,</hi> would no longer aſcribe to her ſuch Principles and Doctrines, which ſhe for many years was ignorant of; wherewith the <hi>Church</hi> hath given great advantage to her Enemies, and receiv'd nothing but Scorn and Contempts, and by which ſhe may oblige the preſent <hi>Government</hi> to treat her with leſs kindneſs, than ſhe might otherwiſe expect. But I forget that I am writing a Letter, and how much pardon I already need for running it into ſo great a length; but I thought it better to give you ſo long a trouble in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than to leave any trouble on your mind unremoved: I beſeech you to excuſe candidly the miſtakes I may have committed; and to accept the Services of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Reverend Sir <hi>London</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 1688/9</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate Brother and Faithful Friend,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:96317:20"/>
               <head>Books Lately Printed for <hi>RIC. CHISWELL.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AN Explication of the Catechiſm of the Church of <hi>England, Viz.</hi> The Creed, Lords Prayer, Ten Commandements, and the Sacraments. in IV. Volumes <hi>Fol.</hi> by <hi>Gabr. Towerſon,</hi> D. D.</p>
               <p>The Fifteen <hi>Notes</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as laid down by Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> examined and confuted by ſeveral Hands with a Table to the whole. <hi>4to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reflexions upon the Books of the Holy Scripture in order to eſtabliſh the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion, in Two Parts, <hi>Oct.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Alix:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>TEXTS</hi> which the Papiſts cite out of the <hi>Bible</hi> for Proof of the Points of their Religion <hi>Examined,</hi> and ſhew'd to be alledg'd without Ground. In twenty five diſtinct Diſcourſes, by ſeveral Hands, <hi>Viz.</hi> Popery not founded in Scripture, The Introduction. TEXTS concerning the Obſcurity of Holy Scriptures. —Of the inſufficiency of Scripture, and neceſſity of Tradition. — Of the Supremacy of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Pope, over the whole Church. <hi>In two parts.</hi> —Of Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. —Of the Worſhip of Angels and Saints departed, <hi>In two Parts.</hi> —Of the Worſhip of Images and Reliques. —Of the Seven Sacraments, and the Efficacy of them: <hi>In two Parts.</hi> —Of the Sacrifice of the Maſs: <hi>In two Parts.</hi> —Of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, —Of Auricular Confeſſion. —Of Satisfactions: <hi>In two parts.</hi> —Of Purgatory: <hi>In two Parts.</hi> — Of Prayer in an unknown Tongue: <hi>In two Parts.</hi> —Of Coelibacy of Prieſts, and Vows of Continence: <hi>In two parts.</hi> — Of the Viſibility of the Church. — Of Merit of Good Works. <hi>Two Tables to the whole will ſhortly be publiſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Continuation of the ſtate of the Controverſie between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> being a full account of the Books that have been of late written on both ſides. By <hi>William Wake</hi> M. A. <hi>4to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Patricks</hi> Parable of the Pilgrim. The Sixth Edition corrected.</p>
               <p>— A <hi>Private Prayer</hi> to be uſed in difficult Times. <hi>8to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>— Expoſition of the Ten Commandments: <hi>8to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>— His Sermon before the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> 20. <hi>January</hi> 1688.</p>
               <p>— A Sermon before the Queen at <hi>Whitehall, March</hi> 1. 1688.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Books lately Publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Gilbert Burnet.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Collection of Tracts and Diſcourſes, written after the Diſcovery of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot, from the years 1678, to 1685. To which is added a Letter written to Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> giving an Account of Cardinal <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ools</hi> Secret Powers. The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Powder Treaſon, with a Vindication of the Proceedings thereupon. An Impartial Conſideration of the Five Jeſuites dying Speeches, who were Executed for the Popiſh Plot, 1679.</p>
               <p>A Vindication of the Ordinations of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> In which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that all the Eſſentials of Ordination, according to the Practice of the Primitive and Greek Churches are ſtill retained in our Church.</p>
               <p>Reflexions on the Relation of the Engliſh Reformation lately printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in two Parts. <hi>4to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Animadverſions on the Reflections upon Dr. <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNET</hi>'s Travels. 80,</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:96317:21"/>
               <p>Reflexions on a Paper, intitled his Majeſties Reaſons for withdrawing himſelf from <hi>Rocheſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Enquiry into the preſent State of Affairs, and imparticular, whether we owe Allegiance to the King in theſe Circumſtances? And whether we are bound to Treat with Him, and call Him back or no?</p>
               <p>A Sermon Preached in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Chappel before the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> 23d. <hi>Decemb</hi> 1688.</p>
               <p>A Sermon Preached before the Houſe of Commons 31 <hi>January</hi> 1688 being the Thankſgiving day for the deliverance of this Kingdom from Popery and Arbitrary Power.</p>
               <p>His Eighteen Papers relating to the Affairs of Church and State, during the the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Second. Seventeen whereof were written in <hi>Holland,</hi> and firſt Printed there; the other at <hi>Exeter,</hi> ſoon after the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Landing in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Letter to Mr. <hi>Thevenot.</hi> Containing a Cenſure of Mr. <hi>Le Grand</hi>'s Hiſtory of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi>'s Divorce. To which is added, a Cenſure of Mr. <hi>de Meaux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> Hiſtory of the Variations of the Proteſtant Churches. Together with ſome further Reflections on Mr. <hi>Le Grand.</hi> 1689.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scriptorum Eccleſiaſticorum Hiſtoria Literaria a Chriſto nato uſque ad Saeculum</hi> XIV. <hi>Facili Meth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>do digeſta. Qua de Vita illorum ac Rebus geſtis, de Secta, Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matibus, Elogio, Stylo; de Scriptis genuinis, dubiis, ſuppoſititiis, ineditis, deperditis, Fragmentis; deque variis Operum Editionibus perſpicue agitur. Accedunt Scripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Gentiles, Chriſtiane Religionis Oppugnatores; &amp; cujuſvis Saeculi Breviarium. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruntur ſuis locis Veterum aliquot Opuſcula &amp; Fragmenta, turn Graeca, tum Latina hactenus inedita. Praemiſſa denique Prolegomena, quibus plurima ad Antiquitatis Eccleſiasticae ſtudium ſpectantia traduntur.</hi> Opus Indicibus neceſſariis inſtructum. Autore <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILIELMO CAVE, SS. Theol. Profeſ. Canonico Windeſorienſi. Accedit ab Alia Manu Appendix ab ineunte Saeculo</hi> XIV. <hi>ad Annum uſque</hi> MDXVII. <hi>Fol.</hi> 1689.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
               <p>Whereas a Book, Intituled. FASCICULUS RERUM EXPETEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DARUM ET FUGIENDARUM, with a large Additional APPEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIX, was promiſed by <hi>Richard Chiſwell</hi> the Undertaker to be finiſhed in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas Term laſt; This is to give Notice. That by reaſon of the Sickneſs of the Printer, and ſome neceſſary Avocations of the Publiſher, it has been retar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: But, for the Satisfaction of Subſcribers, the Book will be forty or fifty Sheets more than was promiſed in the Propoſals, which will coſt the Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker 100 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> extraordinary, yet, in Conſideration thereof, he will not expect one penny above the firſt Subſcription price; only craves their patience till the Book can be done, which is now going on with all poſſible ſpeed, and ſo ſoon as finiſhed Notice ſhall be given in the <hi>Gazette.</hi> In the mean time there being ſome few of the Impreſſion not yet ſubſcribed for, ſuch Gentlemen as pleaſe to take the Benefit thereof may be admitted Subſcribers, and may have <hi>Printed Propoſals</hi> for ſending for, at the Roſe and Crown in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Chuch-Yard, or at moſt Bookſellers Shops in City or Country.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:96317:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
